<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<digitalEditions>
    <projects>
        <projectData xml:id="1">
            <revisionDesc>
                <date type="entry-added" when="2015-11-15" resp="#us #sm #tz">entry added</date>
            </revisionDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <title/>
                <country/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="project-start"></date>
                    <date type="project-end"></date>
                    <date type="project-update"></date>
                </dates>
                <links>
                    <url target="http://example.com"/>
                </links>
                <desc source="..." resp="...">
                    <kelliaRating points="">KELLIA Rating Description</kelliaRating>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Editors</resp>
                        <person>
                            <name>..</name>
                            <email>..</email>
                        </person>
                        <person>
                            <name>..</name>
                            <email>..</email>
                        </person>
                    </respStmt>
                    <goal>critical edition etc.</goal>
                    <institution role="funding etc.">DFG</institution>
                    <textSource>
                        <lang></lang>
                        <genre></genre>
                        <epoche></epoche>
                    </textSource>
                </desc>
                <dataDesc>
                    <dataSet url="http://url-to-data.com" when="date of the data">
                        <api xml:base="url">Kurzbeschreibung der API</api>
                        
                    </dataSet>
                </dataDesc>
            </projectDesc>
            
        </projectData>
    </projects>
    <!-- ######### -->
    <projects>
        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>InsAph - Inscriptions of Aphrodisias Project</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Bodard, Gabriel</name>
                <name role=""/>
                <name role=""/>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html"> Betreut von Gabriel Bodard
                et al., London, King's College London / Centre for Computing in the Humanities,
                2005-. Projekt zur verteilten Internet-Edition der Inschriften von Aphrodisias auf
                der Grundlage eines community-spezifischen XML-Dialekts für epigraphische Texte
                (Epidoc) und in Verbindung mit archäologischen Informationen. Die teilweise bereits
                im Druck edierten Inschriften werden in das Projekt eingebunden und elektronisch neu
                herausgegeben (Beispiel).</desc>
            <data date="2004">
                <dataSet type="encoded-text" format="xml">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <formatDesc type="standard">EPIDOC</formatDesc>
                        <url>http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/redist/inscriptions/inscriptions.zip</url>
                        <comment>download files as *.zip archive</comment>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
                <dataSet type="digital-text" format="html">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <url>http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/inscription/index.html</url>
                        <comment>"The inscriptions can be viewed by number, by section, by date, by
                            location, by type of text, and by type of monument."</comment>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
            </data>
            <data date="2007">
                <dataSet type="encoded-text" format="xml">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <formatDesc type="standard">EPIDOC</formatDesc>
                        <url type="base-uri">http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/xml/</url>
                        <samples url="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/xml/iAph010001.xml"/>
                        <comment>API: "We have also made all of the XML files available online at
                            this website via a direct URL http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/xml/
                            followed by the inscription filename in the form iAph+6-digit
                            number+.xml. You may download these files, or point your database or XML
                            processor directly to them and generate the results elsewhere. These
                            files validate to the EpiDoc DTD version 5, which is online both at the
                            Stoa and on this site."</comment>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
                <dataSet type="digital-text" format="html">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <url>http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/inscriptions/index.html</url>
                        <comment>"Slightly more than 1 500 inscriptions—about one-third previously
                            unpublished—are presented in this edition of the Inscriptions of
                            Aphrodisias. The texts are numbered by location, with each major
                            monument or zone of the site given a chapter heading (between 1 and 15);
                            the primary table of contents lists the files in this order."</comment>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
            </data>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.stoa.org/hippo/">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>The Confessions of Augustine: An Electronic Edition</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">O'Donnell, James J.</name>
                <name role="">Mahoney, Anne</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html"> Text and commentary by
                James J. O'Donnell, o.O., 1992. SGML encoding and HTML conversion by Anne Mahoney
                for the Stoa Consortium, 1999. "Each book of the text has a link to introductory
                commentary on that book, and each section of the text has a link to detailed
                comments on the section. Links within the commentary connect not only to the section
                of text directly being annotated, but also to other parts of the text and
                commentary. Footnotes in the commentary appear at the end of each book; the footnote
                numbers are links from the commentary text to the footnote and from the footnote
                text back to the commentary. Where possible, links have been provided to the texts
                of classical works and Biblical passages cited in the commentary." [from resource]
            </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15"
            url="http://www.augustinus.de/bwo/dcms/sites/bistum/extern/zfa/cags/cag-online.html">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Corpus Augustinianum Gissense a Cornelio Mayer editum</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Mayer, Cornelius</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Hg. von Cornelius Mayer,
                Basel, Schwabe, 1996. ISBN 978-3796509894. Die CD-ROM-Ausgabe beruht auf einer neuen
                Zusammenstellung der jeweils besten verfügbaren Ausgabe. Zusätzlich sind "sämtliche
                Zitate" nach ihrer Herkunft ausgewiesen, das Gesamtœuvre "linguistisch aufbereitet"
                (lemmatisiert) und um eine bibliographische Datenbank der Forschungsliteratur
                erweitert. Der Link zielt auf eine Informationsseite zum immer noch laufenden
                Projekt.</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://nestlealand.uni-muenster.de/">
            <tag>bible ancient nt</tag>
            <title>Digital Nestle-Aland Prototype (Greek New Testament)</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role=""/>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Published by the Institute
                for New Testament Textual Research of University of Münster in collaboration with
                Scholarly Digital Editions and the Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft, Münster / Birmingham
                / Stuttgart, 2003-2005. (offline since 08/06) "The Digital Nestle-Aland is the
                forthcoming electronic version of the standard scholarly edition of the Greek New
                Testament. It offers two major features not available in the printed book: (1)
                Transcripts of important Greek manuscripts of the New Testament, (2) New complete
                apparatus based on these transcripts." [from resource]</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://codexsinaiticus.org/en/">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Codex Sinaiticus</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Milne, Ronald</name>
                <name role="">Tuck, John</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Directed by Ronald Milne
                and John Tuck, London, British Library, 2007. "Codex Sinaiticus is one of the most
                important books in the world. Handwritten well over 1600 years ago, the manuscript
                contains the Christian Bible in Greek, including the oldest complete copy of the New
                Testament." [from resource] The edition contains high-quality images, physical
                descriptions, transcriptions, critical annotations and translations.</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://catullusonline.org/CatullusOnline/index.php">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Catullus Online - An Online Repertory of Conjectures on Catullus</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Kiss, Dániel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Ed. by Dániel Kiss,
                München, Center for Advanced Studies, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität, 2009-2013.
                "This website offers a critical edition of the poems of Catullus, a repertory of
                conjectures on the text, an overview of the ancient quotations from Catullus that
                have independent source value, and high-quality images of some of the most important
                manuscripts." [from resource]</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://pom.bbaw.de/cmg/">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Corpus Medicorum Graecorum / Latinorum</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Brockmann, Christian</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Hg. von Christian
                Brockmann, Berlin, Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2005-2008.
                Das Langzeitunternehmen versucht neue Wege zu gehen. Zu Galen, Kommentar zu
                Hippokrates, Über die Gelenke ist 2005 eine "Probeedition" erschienen, die wahlfreie
                Zusammenstellungen von Handschriftenfaksimiles, neu erstelltem kritischen Text,
                Editions-Apparat, verschiedenen kanonischen Zählungen und Übersetzung
                erlaubt.</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://hyperdonat.tge-adonis.fr/" xml:lang="fr">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Hyperdonat - Une édition électronique des commentaires de Donat aux comédies de
                Térence</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Bureau, Bruno</name>
                <name role="">Ingarao, Maud</name>
                <name role="">Nicolas, Christian</name>
                <name role="">Emmanuelle, Raymond</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Bruno Bureau, Maud Ingarao,
                Christian Nicolas, Emmanuelle Raymond (éds), Lyon, Université Lyon III / ENS de
                Lyon, 2007-2011. "Hyperdonat est originellement un projet d’édition hypertexte du
                commentaire attribué à Aelius Donat aux comédies de Térence. Le projet s’inscrit
                dans une réflexion plus vaste sur l’édition hypertexte de commentaires de nature
                variée. Ce site présente au fur et à mesure les résultats - corpus et
                fonctionnalités - produits au sein du projet." [from resource] For a documentation
                of the project see the blog hyperdonat.hypotheses.org</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://euripidesscholia.org/" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Euripides Scholia</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Mastronarde, Donald J.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Beta version 1 Created by
                Donald J. Mastronarde, Berkeley (CA), University of California Berkeley, 2010. The
                "site is the home of a new open-access digital edition of the scholia on the plays
                of the ancient Athenian tragedian Euripides (born ca. 485-480, died winter 407/406
                BCE). There are [via filters] currently three levels of detail offered: full view
                shows each scholion followed by all public elements that have been provided in the
                edition (not all elements appear for every scholion); expert view shows the same but
                also adds two optional elements intended for the author and collaborators; the view
                with trans. and app. shows only the scholion and a translation (if available) and
                the apparatus criticus (if there are variants). The content can be filtered to
                include everything (prefatory material or arguments and scholia of all kinds); only
                the old scholia (scholia vetera); all scholia except those tagged as glosses ..."
                [from resource] </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title> IRT - The Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania </title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Tripolitania, Roman</name>
                <name role="">Reynolds, J. M.</name>
                <name role="">Ward-Perkins, J. B.</name>
                <name role="">Bodard, Gabriel</name>
                <name role="">Roueché, Charlotte</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Inscriptions of Roman
                Tripolitania, by J. M. Reynolds and J. B. Ward-Perkins, enhanced electronic reissue
                by Gabriel Bodard and Charlotte Roueché (2009). ISBN 978-1-897747-23-0. "The first
                publication of Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania, which appeared in 1952, has long
                been out of print. Produced in post-war conditions, it only included illustrations
                of a few inscriptions, although very many of them had been photographed; and it only
                offered limited geographic information. The purposes of this enhanced reissue are,
                therefore, to make the original material available again, and to provide the full
                photographic record, together with geographical data linking the inscriptions to
                maps and gazetteers, and so to other resources. Electronic publication makes this
                possible, and also allows us to offer greater functionality, such as free text
                searches. We have included the material from the supplement which contained further
                texts, numbered in the same sequence (973-996): 'Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania:
                a supplement', published in PBSR 23 (1955), 124-147, and we have incorporated
                corrections and emendations made in that article; but we have not attempted to alter
                or emend any item otherwise. The indices of this edition are generated from the
                texts themselves. This means that in some cases they will diverge from those in the
                original edition, usually being fuller: but the material in three texts not included
                in that edition (261, 262 and 855) and the Neo-Punic personal names do not appear in
                these indices." [from resource] </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/index.html" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>IOSPE - Ancient Inscriptions of the Northern Black Sea</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Ivantchik, Askold</name>
                <name role="">Polinskaya, Irene</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Northern Black Sea Directed
                by Askold Ivantchik and Irene Polinskaya, London: King's College London, 2011. "The
                aims of the project include a new study of all Ancient Greek and Latin inscriptions
                originating from the Northern Coast of the Black Sea; and publication of Russian and
                English critical editions of the inscriptions in print and digital formats. [...]
                The new conception of the IOSPE corpus consists in capturing in its entirety the
                ancient epigraphic production of the northern Pontic region – that is, not only
                inscriptions made on stone (lapidary inscriptions), but also on other media and
                fabrics, such as ceramics, metal, and bone. [...] The first stage of the project
                involves publication of Lapidary Inscriptions. There will be about 5,000 lapidary
                texts published in IOSPE, about three times as many as in the original corpus."
            </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.digitalmishnah.umd.edu/" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Digital Mishnah</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Lapin, Hayim</name>
                <name role="">Brown, Travis</name>
                <name role="">Muñoz, Trevor</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Developed by Hayim Lapin,
                with Travis Brown and Trevor Muñoz. College Park (MD): MITH (Maryland Institute for
                Technology and the Humanities) 2012-2013. "The Digital Mishnah Project will provide
                users with a database of digitized manuscripts of the Mishnah from around the world,
                along with tools for collation, comparison, and analysis. This demo provides fully
                marked up transcriptions of twenty-two witnesses to a sample chapter, Bava Metsia ch
                2, and illustrates basic functionalities. In a number of cases, the witnesses
                available for browse expand beyond the sample chapter to include all of Bava Qamma,
                Bava Metsi'a, and Bava Batra." [from resource] </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://mama.csad.ox.ac.uk/" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Monumenta Asiae Minoris Antiqua XI - Monuments from Phrygia and Lykaonia</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Thonemann, Peter</name>
                <name role="">Crowther, Charles</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Peter Thonemann and Charles
                Crowther, Centre for the Study of Ancient Documents, Oxford: University of Oxford,
                Version 1.0, 2012 "Monumenta Asiae Minoris Antiqua (MAMA) XI [is] a corpus of 387
                inscriptions and other ancient monuments from Phrygia and Lykaonia, recorded by Sir
                William Calder (1881-1960) and Dr Michael Ballance (†27 July 2006) in the course of
                annual expeditions to Asia Minor in 1954-1957. The MAMA XI project has been funded
                by a grant from the Arts and Humanities Research Council, and is based at the Centre
                for the Study of Ancient Documents in Oxford." [from resource] </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.mqdq.it/mqdq/" xml:lang="en it">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>musique deoque</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Mastandrea, Paolo</name>
                <name role="">Perrelli, Raffaele</name>
                <name role="">Biondi, Gilberto</name>
                <name role="">Zurli, Loriano</name>
                <name role="">Viparelli, Valeria</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Project lead by Paolo
                Mastandrea, Raffaele Perrelli, Gilberto Biondi, Loriano Zurli and Valeria Viparelli,
                [no publishing place or institution mentioned], 2007 "The 'Musisque Deoque. A
                digital archive of Latin poetry, from its origins to the Italian Renaissance'
                Research Project, was established at the end of 2005. Its aims is to create a
                singular Latin poetry’s database, supplemented and updated with critical apparatus
                and exegetical equipments." [from resource] </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://vindolanda.csad.ox.ac.uk/" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title> Vindolanda Tablets Online </title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Bowman, Alan</name>
                <name role="">Crowther, Charles</name>
                <name role="">Pearce, John</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Directed by Alan Bowman,
                Charles Crowther and John Pearce, Oxford, Oxford University, 2001-2003. Digitale
                Ausgabe der Vindolanda-Fragmente: römische Wachstafeln (und Holztafeln) des 1./2.
                Jahrhunderts aus einer archäologischen Grabung am Hadrianswall. "The website
                includes texts, translations, notes and new high-resolution 'zoomable' digital
                images of all the published tablets. A virtual exhibition draws on the texts and
                archaeological evidence from Vindolanda and other sites on Britain's northern
                frontier to introduce the content and context of the tablets to a non-specialist
                audience. Other resources within the website include a reference guide to
                specialised aspects of Roman life encountered in these documents, such as currency
                and military terminology, the scholarly introductions to the tablets and an account
                of the creation of digital texts and images." [from resource] </desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.cmcl.it/" xml:lang="en it">
            <tag>copt ancient letter</tag>
            <title>CMCL - Corpus dei Manoscritti Copti Letterari</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Tito, Orlandi</name>
                <name role="">Bresciani, Edda</name>
                <name role="">Camplani , Alberto </name>
                <name role="">Emmel, Stephen </name>
                <name role="">Layton , Bentley </name>
                <name role="">Pericoli Ridolfini , Francesco S.</name>
                <name role="">Simonetti, Manlio</name>
                <name role="">Buzi , Paola </name>
                <name role="">Suciu , Alin</name>
                <name role="">Atanassova , Diliana</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Unter der Leitung von Tito
                Orlandi, Rom / Hamburg, Università di Roma und Hiob Ludolf Zentrum Hamburg,
                2003-2004. "The CMCL is an enterprise dedicated to the study of Egyptian Christian
                culture in the I-XII centuries C.E., especially for the documents in Coptic
                language. This web site contains the archives of the CMCL: texts, grammar, history
                of literature, catalogue of manuscripts, bibliography." [from resource] Die
                Online-Publikationen sind nur auf Subskriptionsbasis zugänglich.</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.corimu.unisi.it/" xml:lang="en it">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>Corpus Rhythmorum Musicum (saec. IV-IX) - I</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Stella, Francesco</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Ed. by Francesco Stella et
                al, Siena, Università degli studi di Siena ad Arezzo, 2009. Contains manuscript
                descriptions and images (forthcoming?), manuscript transcriptions ("diplomatic" and
                "half diplomatic"), critical texts with apparatus, concordances, statistical data
                (on linguistic phenomena).</desc>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.abdn.ac.uk/bestiary/" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title>The Aberdeen Bestiary</title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Beavan, Iain</name>
                <name role="">Arnott, Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html"> Ed. by Iain Beavan,
                Michael Arnott et al., Aberdeen, University of Aberdeen, 1995-. Umfassende Edition
                mit Faksimile, Transkription, Übersetzung, Kommentar, Einleitung, kodikologische
                Beschreibung, Index, Bibliografie, Suchmaske. Allerdings versteht sich das Projekt
                selbst nicht als "definitive edition of the text", sondern als Arbeitsmittel für den
                Benutzer.</desc>
            <data formats="html">
                <comment>no exchange data-formats</comment>
            </data>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://www.janeausten.ac.uk/index.html" xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title> Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts Digital Edition </title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Beavan, Iain</name>
                <name role="">Arnott, Michael</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html"> Ed. by Kathryn Sutherland
                et al., London, Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London, 2011.
                "The Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts Digital Edition gathers together in the
                virtual space of the web some 1100 pages of fiction written in Jane Austen’s own
                hand. Through digital reunification, it is now possible to access, read, and compare
                high quality images of original manuscripts whose material forms are scattered
                around the world in libraries and private collections. [...] The main resources in
                the digital edition are the manuscripts themselves, accessed through the manuscript
                menu and grouped chronologically and according to their material states as fair
                copies (the Juvenilia and Lady Susan), working drafts (The Watsons, Persuasion,
                Sanditon), and further materials. Each manuscript can be opened in a variety of
                ways: as facsimile pages which can be magnified using ‘zoomify’; as transcribed text
                set side by side with the original manuscript page; or through a Headnote that
                provides details of the manuscript’s history and physical description." [from
                resource] </desc>
            <data>
                <dataSet type="encoded-text" format="xml">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <comment>xml-data not directly available</comment>
                        <formatDesc type="standard">TEI</formatDesc>
                        <url/>
                        <schema url="http://www.janeausten.ac.uk/redist/JA_encoding_model.pdf"/>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
                <dataSet type="metadata" format="xml">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <formatDesc type="standard">METS</formatDesc>
                        <url/>
                        <schema url=""/>
                        <comment>manuscript images' metadata; <ref
                                target="http://www.janeausten.ac.uk/edition/technical.html">"The
                                metadata was automatically extracted from the images using the
                                ImageMagick and ExifTool software, and the METS files were generated
                                from these using XSLT, with a custom Python script acting as glue to
                                this process."</ref></comment>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
                <dataSet type="digital-text" format="html">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <url>http://www.janeausten.ac.uk/index.html</url>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
            </data>
        </project>

        <project entryDate="2015-11-15" url="http://diglib.hab.de/edoc/ed000166/start.htm"
            xml:lang="en">
            <tag>ancient</tag>
            <title> Jacques de Fonteny's Livre d'Enigmes - Manuscript of an Early 17th-Century
                Para-Emblematic, Illustrated Sonnet Sequence. </title>
            <links>
                <url/>
            </links>
            <respStmt>
                <name role="">Strasser, Gerhard F.</name>
                <name role="">Glaser, Eva Christina</name>
            </respStmt>
            <desc url="http://www.digitale-edition.de/vlet_ancient.html">Ed. by Gerhard F. Strasser,
                assist. by Eva Christina Glaser. Wolfenbüttel: Herzog August Bibliothek, 2012.
                TEI-based digital edition offering facsimile, original transcription, and modern
                french transcription with some prefatory remarks, commentary and bibliography. </desc>
            <data>
                <dataSet type="metadata" format="xml">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <formatDesc type="standard">METS</formatDesc>
                        <url>http://diglib.hab.de/edoc/ed000166/mets.xml</url>
                    </resource>
                    <resource type="processing">
                        <formatDesc type="language">XSLT</formatDesc>
                        <url>http://diglib.hab.de/rules/styles/mets.xsl</url>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
                <dataSet type="encoded-text" format="xml">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <formatDesc type="standard">TEI</formatDesc>
                        <url>http://diglib.hab.de/edoc/ed000166/start.xml</url>
                    </resource>
                    <resource type="processing">
                        <formatDesc type="language">XSLT</formatDesc>
                        <url>http://diglib.hab.de/edoc/ed000166/start.xsl</url>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
                <dataSet type="digital-text" format="html">
                    <resource type="data">
                        <url>http://diglib.hab.de/edoc/ed000166/start.htm</url>
                    </resource>
                </dataSet>
            </data>
        </project>

    </projects>
    <standards>
        <standard xml:id="mets">
            <name>METS</name>
            <url>http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/</url>
            <desc/>
        </standard>
        <standard xml:id="tei">
            <name>TEI</name>
            <url>http://www.tei-c.org</url>
            <desc/>
        </standard>
    </standards>
</digitalEditions>
